i always find it funny as a personal
trainer you know i'll train an
overweight male
and he says i got all this belly fat i
need to do a ton of crunches and side
crunches
i need to get this belly fat off and
while we've known for a very long time
that spot reduction is a myth
you can't burn fat off the area by doing
an exercise that works that area
people still want to do it except in the
case of leg fat i'll train a woman who
carries a lot of fat on their legs and
then they say no
i can't squat or dead lift i don't want
to build my legs anymore and i'll try to
politely tell them like you need to burn
fat you got to get stronger all over
but in her mind she's thinking it's just
going to grow her legs even more whereas
the man is thinking it's going to melt
off all his body fat i just think the
contradiction is interesting
[Music]
[Applause]
let's take one all right almost everyone
knows that spot reduction is a myth
like if i have fat somewhere on my body
i can't just do
a bunch of reps of an exercise that
works that area and then burn fat
off that area that's a myth nevertheless
the tactics endure do you ever laugh at
how when someone wants to lose fat
off their abs they do a bazillion
crunches and side crunches and ab
exercises but when someone wants to lose
fat off their legs
they use the exact opposite approach
they say oh i don't want to do squats
and deadlifts they're already too big
you might be thinking this is comparing
apples to oranges because the people
wanting to lose mass off their legs have
too much muscle
but in my experience it's almost always
too much fat anyway it's just kind of
contradictory but regardless
doing crunches won't help you lose fat
off your abs doing
leg extensions and leg curls won't help
you lose fat off your legs and avoiding
squats and deadlifts
won't help you lose fat off your legs
either you lean out by eating a deficit
keeping your protein high and getting
stronger through progressive overload
let's take a hypothetical 130 pound
woman or
200-pound man the man starts out at 25
body fat the woman starts out at 30
body fat they lift weights for a year
they eat at maintenance
they stay the same weight the man puts
on 10 pounds of muscle the woman puts on
six and a half pounds of muscle that man
is now 20
body fat not 25 and he looks a lot
leaner
and the woman she's no longer 30 body
fat she's now 25
body fat and she looks leaner too but
here's the deal
both of them shrunk in size you see
muscle is denser than fat
so at equal weights muscle takes up less
space than fat so if you eat at a
maintenance and gain a ton of strength
and get stronger through progressive
overload
you will build muscle lose fat stay the
same weight on the scale but actually
get
smaller you'll be a smaller version of
yourself
and you'll be smaller especially in the
problem areas
like the midsection the thighs places
where people tend to store fat so this
is why i'm a big fan of
total body training in fact one of my
goals for the future is to promote the
sport i developed
which i call strong lifting and strong
lifting is like power lifting but power
lifting is three exercises squats bench
deadlifts
strong lifting is six exercises
it's squats bench deadlifts and then
also chin ups military press
and hip thrusts and i just think strong
lifting is a better idea
because if you just train for power
lifting you're not gonna maximally
develop all your muscles
but if you train for strong lifting you
will you hit squats bench and deads
you hit most of the muscles in your body
but you need a little extra
shoulder work that's where the military
press comes in you need a little bit
extra work for your lats
that's where the chin up comes in and
you need a little more extra for your
glutes
that's where the hip thrust comes in so
these are the best six lifts in my
opinion to work the entire body and
cause you to gain mass
or recomp depending on how you're eating
and basically lead to your best physique
possible so
in strong lifting we squat and dead i
love squats and deadlifts
always have always will and i also am a
big champion of
training for performance i know when i
started training for performance and not
trying to
body build so much i quit trying to
isolate so much and
work every muscle from every angle and i
focus on gaining strength
my physique improved and i've noticed
the same with thousands of clients that
i've trained over the last couple of
decades nevertheless there are times
when somebody i train doesn't want to
grow their legs they want to grow their
glutes without growing their legs
hence the title of this video how to
grow your glutes without growing your
legs and i first wrote a blog post on
this exact topic
in june of 2013 that was eight freaking
years ago
and since then half the female fitness
influencers who are on youtube have made
videos on this exact topic
and i haven't yet made a youtube video
so i decided that time was right maybe
you want to hear it from the horse's
mouth
how should you best train to grow your
glutes without growing your leg now my
system has evolved since 2013 but
it's still pretty much the same but
before i dive into that
a word of caution most people who assume
they shouldn't
train their legs hard actually should
because as i mentioned before
a lot of them carry a lot of fat on
their legs and that's not muscle
they do need muscle there and they need
to be eating in a deficit
to lose weight but they need to be
training as hard as possible and eating
a lot of protein
to hold on to as much muscle as possible
so that the weight they lose is fat you
want
fat loss not weight loss so you lose 20
pounds you don't want to lose
10 pounds of fat and 10 pounds of muscle
you want to lose
20 pounds of fat keep all your muscle
that's how you're going to be the
leanest that's going to be how you're
going to have the best body composition
and look your best and in order to keep
your muscle you got to train
really really hard it's not easy to keep
your muscle and lose just fat for weight
loss i mean i've trained a ton of bikini
olympians and they all did squats in
deadlifts and lunges
now granted they're not squatting you
know 315
but typically you know they'll do like
95 pounds or 115 pounds
they'll do like sets of 10. you might
see them use the smith machine as well
but they do do their squats every week
they do their stiff leg deadlifts and
their rdls
you know you'll see them do lunge and
single leg squat variations all the time
my point is these women arguably have
the best physiques out there and they're
not avoiding training their legs they
just keep it in balance and they have
low body fat levels
so you want to get down to lower body
fat levels before you decide if you're
too muscular or not because chances are
you're not you just need to lose a lot
of fat
that being said there are indeed
individuals who should train uniquely
for their goals
and should avoid training their legs too
hard and should focus more on the glutes
let's talk about the glute to leg size
ratio
let's say you want to grow your glutes
but you hammer squats deadlifts lunges
leg press
leg extensions and leg curls and let's
say you just have poor
genetics for building glutes but you
have good genetics for growing your legs
say your glutes don't get that much
bigger but your quads get a lot bigger
your hamstrings get a lot bigger your
adductors get bigger now even though
your glutes didn't shrink they actually
look
smaller because they're proportionately
smaller because it's the ratio
that creates that visual illusion so
people have good
muscle building genetic potential for
growing their legs but not so good of
potential for growing their glutes
they're good contenders
for this protocol now models also fall
into this category
in that if they get their legs too big
they're out of a job
you know their agency will cut them you
just can't have huge legs and be a model
and also just some people who
consistently get hurt from squats and
deadlifts
and they're in this constant pain cycle
who can never seem to rid themselves of
these nagging
pain and injuries you know in the low
back the hips the knees
because let's face it squats and deads
are the hardest exercise for a good
reason
they work the muscles best but because
they work the muscles so hard they
produce a lot of joint stress
sometimes it's very good to take like
three months and just really focus on
growing your glutes
because the exercises that isolate the
glutes tend to be low stress and well
tolerated
and something about the glutes just
helps keep the body in check
now you know they're kind of like the
centerpiece or the keystone muscle of
body the right smack in the middle
they tie into a lot of things up and
down the body
and from a functional anatomy
perspective they do a lot of good things
for the body you know they help protect
the si joint the low back the hips
the knees so if you fall into one of the
categories i mentioned
then you will benefit from the methods
i'm about to describe all right so how
do you grow your glutes without growing
your legs it's hard to do so because
you know the glutes are hippic sensors
so anytime you extend the hips you're
going to use your glutes but you also
use the hamstrings and adductors they're
also hip extensors so anytime you do hip
extension
you're going to use your hammies and
adductors to some degree and they're
also synergists when you perform
hip abduction and even hip external
rotation
you're never truly fully isolating the
glutes but you can indeed bias the
glutes so if you want to increase your
glute to leg size ratio
you're going to want to do two things
the first thing is to avoid
exercises that highly activate your
quads hamstrings and adductors and the
second thing you want to do is make sure
you're performing
exercises that highly activate the
glutes without simultaneously highly
activating the leg muscles so where does
this leave us
all right exercise you want to avoid
squats are out and this includes all the
squat variations you know back squats
front squats
box squats avoid them for now also
excluded are all
single leg squatting movements like
lunges bulgarian split squats
step ups skater squats pistols single
leg box squats
and also common bodybuilding movements
for the quads
you're not going to do any hack squats
no leg presses and no leg extensions
all those exercises hammer the quads
just don't do them for now
you're also going to avoid hamstring
movements okay so no deadlift variations
even sumo deads don't do them even trap
bar deads don't do them
you know deadlifts stiff leg deadlifts
romanian deadlifts
they're out good mornings they're also
out all the leg curl variations you know
lying seated kneeling don't do them and
also nordic ham crows and glue ham
raises
they must be avoided and finally you're
gonna avoid hip adduction movements
like the seated hip adduction machine
now that's not to be confused with a
seated hip
abduction machine that's good to do now
you might be wondering right now
what about hip thrusts now hip thrusts
are kind of tricky because
people think hip thrust oh they're such
a great glute exercise they're a glute
isolation movement no they're not
they hammer the quads and they also hit
the adductors and hammies pretty good
so if you're the type that feels hipped
us all in your glutes and not so much in
your legs then have atom but if you do
feel hypnus highly activating your quads
or your adductors or hammies then you
should probably avoid them for a few
months alright where does that leave us
what exercises
should we be doing your main weapon is
the barbell glute bridge you're gonna be
a glute bridging machine
and you can do barbell glute bridges
three days a week in different rep
ranges
you can also do feet elevated glute
bridges those work very well
all hip abduction movements are good to
do these include frontal plane and
transverse plane hip abduction movements
so ones where you're straight up
and ones where you're bent over and
there are tons of these movements you
know
the seated hip abduction machine cable
standing hip abductions sideline hip
raises
extra range sideline hip abductions and
all the band exercises that are popular
lateral band walks bands seated hip
abduction band hip hinge abductions that
are all good to do
hip extra rotation exerciser in there's
only one main hip external rotation
exercise we do and that's the cable cuff
hip external rotation but that targets
the glutes very well all right i know i
said
avoid all deadlifts but there is a
deadlift that i do like in this
circumstance and that's the american
deadlift with the american deadlift you
do way more pelvic tilting you're going
lighter you're not working the
hamstrings quite as much you're working
the glutes harder you're going to do
cable kickbacks you can also do
kickbacks with bands
you can do back extensions but not the
standard way you're doing it
the glute dominant way with your feet
flared out and your upper back rounded
cable pull throughs are good to do
reverse hyper variations are good to do
so this includes frog reverse hypers
spread eagle reverse hypers
and knee banded reverse hypers frog
pumps are great to do
around two-thirds of people like frog
pumps one third don't if you're a frog
pump responder
bust them out if not avoid them and
finally
glue squeezes like rkc planks or
staining glute squeezes
yes they're isometrics but they work
well in this scenario all right so i
told you what exercise to be doing
how you put that together in a program
that's up to you
i've went over some programming stuff in
another video i have discussed program
design topics already
i did so in my video how often should
you train the glutes i did so in my rule
of thirds video
if you're looking for a cookie cutter
program to follow i actually made an
e-book with the same title how to grow
your glutes without growing the legs
that walks you through a 12-week
protocol but in general train your
glutes three days a week
and try to include a variety of
exercises like hip dose variations
different hip extension exercises and
different hip abduction external
rotation exercises now in a perfect
world we'd have all this data like
you'd take a ton of different exercises
and you would look at their
mean or peak glute activation according
to emg electromyography and then you'd
also look at the activation of the
quadriceps
the hammies the adductors and then you
calculate the ratio of all those
in this way you could see oh this is a
big bang for your buck movement it works
mostly the glutes or yes this exercise
works the glutes well
but it also hammers the quads or the
hammies or something like that but i've
done enough emg work and i've spent so
much time in the gym
training myself and others that i think
this list is pretty comprehensive and
pretty complete like i'm sure my system
will evolve 10 years from now i'll look
at this and i'll say
that was pretty good but we know more
now so i'll tweak it a little bit
even knowing that my system probably
isn't perfect it's still the most
effective program to date at targeting
the glutes and avoiding leg development
so if you're interested in primarily
growing your glutes without tacking on
any additional leg mass then give these
strategies a try
and make sure you start off slow when
you begin training this way
give yourself some time to grow start
off light really feel the glutes
squeezing and you eventually want to be
very strong
at these glute exercises don't forget to
use progressive overload or you won't
grow your glutes okay that's a wrap
if you like what you saw please make
sure you give it a thumbs up also
please leave me a comment i'm trying my
best to answer and definitely make sure
you're subscribed to my channel because
i have a lot to come
in 2021 thanks for watching so to help
you guys out with this
i created this pdf that tells you which
exercise to avoid and which ones to
focus on
and you can download it just by clicking
on the link in the caption
now if this video intrigued you and you
would like to train
under my system using my principles then
i invite you to click on the link below
and subscribe to booty by brett and join
the thousands of other happy members
who are seeing amazing results